[MUSIC]
[음악]
So the first thing we need to describe is how are we gonna represent the documents
우선 문서를 어떻게 표현하는지
that we're looking at.
설명드리겠습니다
Okay, so perhaps the most popular model to represent a document is something called
아마 문서 표현에 가장 인기있는 방법은
the bag of words model,
bag-of-words(단어주머니) 모델인데
where we simply ignore the order of words that are present in the document.
문서에서 단어 순서를 무시하는 방식입니다
And the reason it's called a bag of words model is we think of taking a bag,
bag-of-words 모델이라 불리는 이유는
throwing all the words from that document into the bag, shaking it up, and
주머니에다 문서의 모든 단어를 쓸어넣고
the new document we've created with the words all jumbled up
뒤섞은 다음 새로운 문서를 만들어도
has exactly the same representation as I'll describe
원 문서에서 순서대로 정리된 단어와
as the original document where the words were ordered.
정확히 같은 표현이 되기 때문이죠
And what we're gonna do, instead of considering the structure,
다음으로 단어 순서 같은 구조를
the order of the words,
고려하기보다 문서에 등장하는
is we're simply gonna count the number of instances of every word in the document.
모든 단어의 등장 빈도를 셉니다
So let's look at a specific example of this.
구체적인 예를 한번 들어보죠
So in this document we're gonna imagine that there's just one sentence, and that
이 문서에서 문장 하나만 있다고 가정하고
sentence says that Carlos calls the sport futbol, Emily calls the sport soccer.
문장은 Carlos calls the sport futbol, Emily calls the sport soccer입니다
Actually I guess that's really two sentences, but that's the entire document.
실제로는 두 문장 같지만 아무튼 이게 문서 전체입니다
And what we're gonna do to count the number of instances
이제 이 짧은 문서에서
of words in this very short document is we're just gonna look at a vector.
단어 빈도를 세서 벡터로 만듭니다
And this vector is defined over the vocabulary
벡터는 대상 언어의
in whatever language we're looking at.
사전으로 정의됩니다
So maybe one word in our vocabulary is the name, Carlos.
사전에서 단어 하나는 이름인 Carlos일지도 모르죠
Another place in this vector is the index for the word sport.
벡터에는 sport란 단어의 인덱스도 어딘가 있을 겁니다
And then, somewhere else we have the word futbol luckily in our English vocabulary
And then, somewhere else we have the word futbol luckily in our English vocabulary 운좋게도 futbol이란 단어가 영어 사전에 있고
that I'm writing here and then let's say, Emily is this last entry.
Emily가 마지막 항목이라고 하죠
What words are we missing?
어떤 단어가 빠졌죠?
We're missing the word calls, and of course the word the.
calls와 the가 빠졌죠
Okay, so how many instances of Carlos?
Carlos가 몇 개 있죠?
Well, there's only one.
하나밖에 없죠
How many instances of the?
the가 몇 개 있죠?
We have two of the.
the는 두 개 있죠
Two of calls, two of sports,
calls 두 개, sport 두 개
one of futbol and I forgot the word soccer.
futbol 하나, 그리고 soccer를 잊었는데 하나죠
One word of Emily and let just throw soccer in here,
Emily 하나, 여기서 soccer를 넣고
imagining this was the index and this would be our word count factor with.
이게 인덱스라 가정하면 단어수 벡터는 이런 모습이겠죠
For this document, every other entry would be zero.
문서에서 다른 모든 항목은 0이 됩니다
And all these other entries represent all the other words that are out there in
다른 항목은 고양이, 개, 나무처럼
the vocabulary, like the word cat, and
사전에는 있지만 문서에 등장하지 않는
dog, and tree, and every other word you can think of.
단어를 나타냅니다
So it's a very, very long and
등장하는 단어수를 세는
sparse vector that counts the number of words that we see in this document.
아주아주 커다란 희소벡터입니다
Okay, so we talked about this representation of our documents in terms
단어수만으로 문서를 표현하는 방법을
of just these raw word counts.
알아봤습니다
This bag of words model.
bag-of-words 모델입니다
And now we want to talk about how we're gonna measure the similarity between
여러 문서 사이의 유사도를 측정하는 법을
different documents because we're gonna use that in order to find
알아볼 텐데 문서가 서로 얼마나 연관되어 있나
documents that are related to one another and so on, like we talked about before.
알기 위해 필요하기 때문입니다
Carlos is reading an article, so what’s another article he might be interested in?
카를로스가 기사를 읽는데 그가 관심을 가질만한 기사가 어떤 게 있을까요?
Okay, so imagine that this is the count factor that we have for
이게 축구와 유명 아르헨티나 선수
this article on soccer, with this famous Argentinian player, Messi.
메시에 대한 기사의 카운트 벡터라고 할게요
And then there's another article here that I'm showing in blue and
파란색을 칠한 또 다른 기사와
the associated word counts.
그에 딸린 단어수입니다
And this article is about another famous soccer player, Pele.
이 기사는 또 다른 유명 축구선수 펠레에 관한 것입니다
Is that right?
발음이 맞나요?
>> Pele.
>> 펠레
[LAUGH] So when we think about measuring similarity,
[웃음] 유사도를 측정할 때
what we can do is simply look at an element-wise product over this vector.
벡터의 스칼라곱을 계산합니다
So for every element in the vector, we're gonna
벡터의 모든 항에 대해
multiply the two elements appearing in these two different count vectors.
두 단어수 벡터 각각의 항을 곱합니다
And add up over all the different elements in this vector.
그리고 전체를 더합니다
So here I've done this math where we have 1 times 3,
이렇게 계산하면 1 곱하기 3,
all the other elements multiplied to 0,
다른 항들은 곱하면 0이 되고
except at some point that fifth entry in the vector we have 5 times 2.
5번째 항에 5 곱하기 2가 있습니다
And if we do this multiplication over the whole vector,
벡터 전체에 곱셈을 하면
the sum of these terms is 13.
모든 항의 합은 13이 됩니다
So that measures the similarity between these two articles on soccer.
축구 기사 둘 사이의 유사도를 측정해봤습니다
But now let's compare to another article,
이제 다른 기사와 비교할 건데
which happens to be something about a conflict in Africa.
아프리카의 분쟁이 주제입니다
And so I'm providing the examples of word counts that appear in this article.
이 기사에 등장하는 단어수를 예를 들어볼게요
And what we see, is when we go to measure the similarities between these articles,
이 기사 간의 유사도 측정법인 스칼라곱으로
using the method that I described of element-wise product, and
곱하고 더하면 유사도는
then adding, that the similarity here in this case is 0.
이 경우 0이 됩니다
Okay, so let's talk about an issue that arises when we
단어수로 문서 간의 유사도를
use these raw word counts to measure the similarity between documents.
측정할 때 나타나는 문제를 알아보죠
So to do this, let's look at these green and blue articles that we had before.
그러기 위해 초록, 파란 기사를 다시 봅니다
And so I'm repeating the word count vectors that we had, and
단어수 벡터와 계산으로 돌아가보면
what we calculated before was the fact that the similarity between these two
똑같이 축구가 주제인 두 기사 간의 유사도는
articles that are both about soccer is 13.
13으로 나옵니다
Okay, but
그러면
now let's look at what happens if we simply double the length of the documents.
문서 길이를 두 배로 늘릴 때 어떻게 되나 보죠
So now every word that appeared in that original document appears twice in this
원 문서에서 등장하는 모든 단어는
twice as long document.
새 문서에서 빈도가 두 배가 됩니다
So, the word count vector is simply two times the word count vector we had before.
단어수 벡터는 간단히 원래 벡터의 2배가 되죠
So, when we go to calculate the similarity here,
이렇게 유사도를 다시 계산하면
what we see is now the similarity is calculated to be 52.
유사도는 이제 52로 나옵니다
So, let's think about this.
생각해봅시다
What we're saying is that two documents that
두 문서의 관계는 이전과
are related to each other in the same way as before.
동일합니다
They're both talking about the same two sports, but
같은 스포츠가 주제인데
one just is replicated twice is a lot more similar.
길이가 두 배라고 더 유사하답니다
We would say, yes, Carlos is a lot more interested in this longer document.
카를로스가 긴 문서에 관심 있다고 결론 내릴 수 있겠네요
Then what happened when Carlos was reading the shorter documents.
카를로스가 짧은 문서를 읽고 있었다면 어떻게 되나요
So this doesn't make a lot of sense when we're trying to do document retrieval.
문서 검색에서 그다지 타당한 방법이 아닙니다
And it biases very strongly towards long documents.
긴 문서에 심하게 편향되니까요
So let's think about how we can cope with this.
이걸 어떻게 극복할지 고민해봅시다
So one solution
한 가지 방법은
is very straight forward where we're simply gonna normalize this vector.
아주 간단하게 벡터를 정규화하는 것이죠
So we take this word count vector and
단어수 벡터에서 노름(norm)을
we're gonna compute the norm of the vector.
계산해냅니다
And so if you guys remember computing the norm of a vector,
벡터 노름 계산을 하려면
we simply add the square of every entry in the vector, and then take the square root.
모든 항을 제곱해서 더한 다음 다시 제곱근을 씌우죠
So, in this case,
이 경우
we have the square root of 1 squared plus 5 squared plus 3 squared plus 1 squared.
1 제곱 더하기 5 제곱 더하기 3 제곱 더하기 1 제곱에 제곱근을 씌웁니다
And that happens to be the number and so,
그러면 6이란 숫자가 나오는데
the resulting normalize word count vector is shown on the bottom of the slide here.
정규화된 단어수 벡터가 슬라이드 밑 부분에 나옵니다
And what this does is, it allows us to place all of our articles that we're
모든 대상 기사에 대해 길이와 관계없이
considering, regardless of their length, on equal footing.
동등한 위치를 부여하게 됩니다
And then use this normalized vector when we go to do retrieval.
그런 다음 정규화된 벡터로 검색을 하는 것이죠
[MUSIC]
[음악]